Britte van Tiem

558 McNeil Building 3718 Locust Walk Philadelphia, PA 19104

bvantiem@sas.upenn.edu

PROFILE

I am a doctoral candidate in the Department of Criminology at the University of Pennsylvania. Informed by extensive experience working in prisons and other places of detention, my research aims to deliver the highest-quality evidence on policies and practices that make prisons safer and reduce reoffending. In my PhD thesis, I combine little-used administrative prison data with other administrative and survey data to contribute causal evidence to a fundamental policy debate: what can prisons do to improve public safety? Specifically, I studied experienced prison conditions in the context of a randomized trial and examined the causal impact of prison-based programming on post-release employment. Prior to my PhD, I managed a prison helpline, oversaw the delivery of a large-scale peer support program, monitored conditions of confinement, and advised policymakers on improving wellbeing in prisons in the UK and Ireland.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Criminology, University of Pennsylvania, USA	*2024
Committee: Aaron J. Chalfin (Chair), Charles Loeffler, John Macdonald, Jordan M. Hyatt	* Expected
M.A., Statistics, University of Pennsylvania, USA	2023
M.Phil., Social Anthropology, University of Cambridge, UK	2013
B.A., Liberal Arts & Science, University College Utrecht, NL	2011

JOURNAL ARTICLES (REFEREED)

van Tiem, B. (2023) "The effects of immigration enforcement on traffic stops: Changing driver or police behavior?", *Criminology & Public Policy* 22(3): 457-489 http://doi.org/10.1111/1745-9133.12625

This research asks whether jail-based immigration enforcement leads to the profiling of Hispanics by municipal police. I leverage a natural experiment to examine the effects of 287(g) jail partnerships on traffic stops and arrests by municipal police in North Carolina in the late 2000s. I find that stops of Hispanic drivers fell in the wake of 287(g) agreements, and show that this fall was driven by changes in Hispanic road use. While I cannot unambiguously disentangle police and driver behavior, I find no evidence that municipal police officers increased pretextual stops and arrests of Hispanic drivers.

PAPERS IN PROGRESS (PHD THESIS)

Van Tiem, B. - "Finding work after prison: Do skills gained in prison matter? Evidence from Variation in Availability" – single-authored

The formerly incarcerated are chronically under-employed. Prisons commonly offer vocational training programs that intend to provide individuals with job opportunities in specific occupational sectors. This paper assesses whether the skills gained in vocational training programs move individuals into work in their field of training. Using a unique dataset for individuals released from prisons in one state in the Eastern United States, I exploit the fact that program participation is partly a function of program availability, to

estimate the causal impact of program participation on sector-specific job attainment. My findings suggest that, overall, vocational training programs move individuals into their sectors of training. These effects are driven by individuals receiving training in the food and construction industries.

Van Tiem et al. - "Improving the Quality of Prison Life – Experimental Evidence From a Scandinavian Style Prison Unit " - with Synøve Nygaard Andersen and Jordan M. Hyatt

What interventions improve the quality of prison environments, as assessed by those who are incarcerated there? We leverage a randomized control trial in which incarcerated men were randomly assigned to a transformed housing unit where conditions of confinement differ markedly from regular conditions. Using panel data from a prison climate survey, we test how changing prison conditions affect incarcerated people's satisfaction with their environment. We assess to what extent changes in satisfaction can be explained by self-reported experiences in prison.

PAPERS UNDER REVIEW

Van Tiem et al. - "Measuring Prison Climate Across Contexts: Lessons from a US Administration of the Prison Climate Questionnaire" - with Paul Nieuwbeerta, Synøve N. Andersen, Jordan M. Hyatt and Hanneke Palmen (Under Review at the European Journal of Criminology)

Prison climate surveys are uniquely positioned to identify how the quality of prison life differs both within and between institutions. However, much of this comparative potential remains unrealized, in part because of insufficient evidence that existing survey instruments are suitable for use in different contexts, and that survey data can be reliably compared across contexts. In this paper, we explore the suitability of the Prison Climate Questionnaire (PCQ) for use in the USA by assessing its factor structure, reliability, construct validity, and criterion validity using survey data from Pennsylvania. We compare our findings to previously published psychometric results from the Netherlands and make recommendations for future comparative prison climate research.

Hyatt et al. - "Perceptions of Incarcerated People Regarding Factors Relating to Prison Conditions, Public Health, and Justice" - with Synøve Nygaard Andersen and Jordan M. Hyatt (R&R at Journal of Public Health Policy)

Using data from the Prison Climate Questionnaire (PCQ) obtained from a population-representative sample of incarcerated men in a correctional facility located in the Eastern United States, this study descriptively considers the complex nexus between the carceral context, health, and justice from the perspective of incarcerated people. Respondents report relatively high degrees of isolation, stress, and fear of victimization. Levels of discrimination, from staff and other incarcerated people, are perceived as high on some units though not universally as such. We illustrate how combining administrative data with self-report data derived from survey instruments designed to measure subjective perceptions of prison climate provides a meaningful opportunity for advancing public health and justice policy.

Knorre (r) van Tiem (r) Chalfin* - "Did Violence Against Asian-Americans Rise in 2020? Evidence from a Novel Approach to Measuring Racially Motivated Attacks" - with Aaron J. Chalfin and Alex Knorre, *equal authorship

Working Paper Link

Did anti-Asian violence rise after the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic? Efforts to answer this question are compromised by the inherent difficulty of measuring racially-motivated crimes as well as concerns that reporting of racially-motivated crimes may have changed due to their increased salience during the pandemic. We pursue an alternative approach to studying whether anti-Asian violence rose after March 2020 that addresses each of these concerns. Using data from the FBI's National Incident-Based Reporting System, we study inter-race violence occurring in public spaces. While public violence declined among all

Americans after March 2020, the share of public violence directed at Asian-Americans by people who were previously unknown to them -- or were acquaintances -- rose more than it did for other Americans.

GRANTS

2023 Russel Sage Foundation, Dissertation Research Grant: \$10,000 Working after Prison

PRESENTATIONS AND INVITED TALKS

"Measuring Prison Climate Across Contexts: Lessons from a US Administration of the Prison Climate Questionnaire."

- American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting, Philadelphia PA, November 2023
- NVC conference, Leiden NL, June 2023

"Did Violence Against Asian-Americans Rise in 2020? Evidence from a Novel Approach to Measuring Racially Motivated Attacks."

American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting, Atlanta, November 2022

"The Impact of Changes in Prison Environments on Incarcerated People's Satisfaction with Prison Conditions."

- American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting, Atlanta GA, November 2022
- Howard League conference, Oxford UK, September 2022

"The Effects of Immigration Enforcement on Traffic Stops: Changing Driver or Police Behavior?"

American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting, Chicago IL, November 2021

"Coping with Life in Prison"

• Invited talk at Her Majesty's Prison and Probation Service Suicide and Self-harm Symposium, UK, August 2019.

"Minimizing the impact of exposure to suicide in prison"

Invited talk at the Safer Care in Prison Conference, UK, March 2019

"Preventing Suicide and Self-Harm in Prison and the Listener Scheme"

• Invited talk at the Independent Monitoring Boards Annual Conference. With Sue McAllister, Prison and Probation Ombudsman, UK, February 2019.

NON-ACADEMIC WRITING

"Annual Report of the Independent Monitoring Board at Tinsley House Immigration Removal Centre", public report, National Preventive Mechanism, May 2020. Available here.

"Annual Report of the Independent Monitoring Board at Gatwick Pre-departure Accommodation", public report, National Preventive Mechanism, May 2020. Available here.

"What Brexit Could Mean for Refugee Protection in Britain", Blog Post, openDemocracy, August 2016. Available here.

TEACHING

CRIM602: Criminal Justice Data Analytics (R), University of Pennsylvania (Fall 2022, Teaching Assistant)

• This course covers the tools and techniques necessary to acquire, organize and visualize complex data to answer questions about crime and the criminal justice system. The course covers basic programming techniques, SQL, text mining, regular expressions and geocoding. The course uses R.

CRIM536: Quantitative Methods, University of Pennsylvania (Fall 2021, Teaching Assistant)

This course is an introduction to the practice of statistics in social and behavioral sciences. Topics
covered include the description of social science data; correlation and other forms of association;
bivariate regression; an introduction to probability theory; the logic of sampling; the logic of statistical
inference and significance tests.

PROFESSIONAL POSITIONS

Research Manager – <u>Scandinavia Prison Project</u> (March 2022 – current)

Drexel University, Philadelphia PA, Research Manager

Arnold Ventures Funded

- Led the redesign of the Prison Climate Questionnaire for the American context. Oversaw four waves of PCQ data collection (N = 2625).
- Responsible for collection and analysis of administrative and survey data.
- Managed the work of graduate and undergraduate research assistants and coordinated research team meetings and activities.
- Supported IRB processes, the preparation of funding reports, and ensuring integrity of random assignment processes.

Prisons & Justice Program Manager (September 2016 – October 2019)

Samaritans, London, United Kingdom

- Oversaw the operational delivery of a peer support program and co-led the delivery of helpline services across 141 prisons in four countries, involving 100+ local offices and over 2000 volunteers.
- Managed an annual budget of up to £2m and managed a team of 7 staff. Secured 5 new grants with a combined value of £2.8m.
- Oversaw the development of a new integrated data collection system for all prison-based phone calls.
- Provided policy advice and technical assistance to governments on mental health strategies in prisons.
- Led Samaritans' relationship with national prison and probation services, ombudsmen, and other justice partners in England & Wales, Scotland, Ireland and Northern Ireland.
- Represented Samaritans in high-level stakeholder forums, including the UK's Ministerial Board on Deaths in Custody.

Consultant (March 2016 – September 2019)

Freedom from Torture, London, United Kingdom

- Wrote policy briefs and official correspondence on the impact of re-detention on torture survivors.
- Prepared a submission to a parliamentary inquiry into the quality of asylum accommodation.
- Conducted research on asylum decision making using client data gathered from clinical service provision and legal and welfare advice services.

Learning & Accountability Officer (April 2014 – March 2016) **Monitoring & Evaluation Officer**, maternity cover (October 2013 – April 2014) Amnesty International, London, United Kingdom

- Advised the senior leadership team in the Americas on the development of a regional project portfolio
 after the opening of a new regional office in Mexico City.
- Coordinated the development of the growth pillar of Amnesty International's strategic plan, on how to increase the organization's networks, visibility and political access through its country offices.
- Analyzed project monitoring data for the purposes of internal and external learning and reporting.
- Carried out internal preparations for external impact evaluations of flagship campaigns.

Consultant (January 2012 – September 2012) Intern (June 2011 – December 2011) War Child, Kampala, Uganda

- Wrote a project evaluation report based on project monitoring data collected from 300 life-skills trainings for children and young people in a post-war context.
- Designed and implemented new data-collection methodologies and provided on-the-job coaching to 20 field staff to improve the consistency in the collection and recording of monitoring data.
- Designed and implemented a participatory video methodology with five local partner organizations to enable quality monitoring of a three-year EU-funded life-skills project.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Independent Monitor, public appointment (December 2017 – October 2019) *Independent Monitoring Boards, London, United Kingdom Tinsley House Immigration Removal Centre, Gatwick Pre-Departure Accommodation*

- Monitored the treatment of detainees in immigration removal centers through unescorted visits with full access to people detained, policies and records. Areas monitored included: use of force, safety, fairness of treatment, healthcare, access to legal advice, education, and preparation for release.
- Attended detention centers to follow up on specific instances of segregation and use of force.
- Escalated concerns and advocated for improvements to the management of the detention center during visits and via a monthly board meeting
- Co-authored an annual report to the Secretary of State on conditions and standards in the detention centers monitored.

TECHNICAL SKILLS AND LANGUAGES

Statistical / Methodological Software: R (advanced). Familiarity with Stata and Excel.

Additional Software: Latex/Overleaf

Relevant Coursework (methods): Applied Econmetrics, Applied Health Care Econometrics, Modern

Data Mining, Causal Inference, Sample Survey Methods,

Mathematical Statistics for Criminology, Probability

Languages: English and Dutch (Native), Spanish (Fluent)